Guide to the Issei Oral History Project in Watsonville Collection ARS.0081
Archive of Recorded Sound
- 1. Audiocassettes, 1978-03-29 - 1983-02-10; 37 audiocassettes; Nakane, Kazuko
  - 12. Kokuho Nakamura, 1978-05-07; Nakamura, Kokuho
    He’s the second son of four sons. His eldest brother, Nakamura Heikichi, is 8 years senior to Kokichi. His two younger brothers are Iekichi and Harukichi. There’s a six-year age difference between Kokichi and Iekichi, and another six years between Iekichi and Heikichi. There were several other brothers, but his mother suffered some miscarriages and some of his brothers died very young. His parents fished and farmed. Kokichi came to the United States for the first time in 1919. His eldest brother came to the United States four years before, when he was 27 years old. He came because there was no work in Kagoshima. His other brothers soon followed, along with about 120 people from his hometown. His eldest brother came to downtown Los Angeles. Since he couldn’t speak English, he worked as a gardener and went to night school to learn the language. He was still gardening when Kokichi came. Kokichi lived in Kagoshima Prefecture until he was 12 years old, when he went to Taiwan. He finished school in Taiwan. After that, he taught in Taiwan until he turned 17. Then, Kokichi became ill and went back to Japan.
    After he recovered from his illness, Kokichi came to the United States at the age of 19. He didn’t speak English. He got a job as a truck driver at night and took acting lessons during the day, so he didn't have time to go to night school like his brother. From 8 a.m. until noon, he attended acting school. At 1 p.m., he loaded the truck. At 6 p.m., he brought the cargo to the market and worked until midnight. From midnight until 3 a.m., he sold his goods at the market. After that, he went home to sleep, waking up in time for his acting lessons. During those times he slept very little. On Saturdays, he slept until 9 am and then taught in a Japanese Saturday school. On Sundays, as he’s a Christian, he taught in Sunday school. That was his life until he got married 10 years after he arrived in the United States. He got married in Japan in an arranged marriage and at the time of the interview they had recently celebrated their 50th wedding anniversary in Los Angeles. His wife was from the town next to his hometown and didn’t have any reservations about coming to the United States. But since Kokichi was into acting, which is not known as a stable job, her family was worried about her. His wife is 8 years younger. At the time of the interview, she was 77 years old. When she married Kokichi, she was 21 or 22. She went to school in Japan. Kokichi came to Los Angeles via a ship called the Kasato-maru. At that time, only 4,000-5,000 Japanese were living in Los Angeles. There was an active Japanese association that held picnics, New Year’s gatherings, etc. The second time Kokichi came to the United States, he was with his wife and used a ship called Shunyo-maru. They heard the news of the attack on Pearl Harbor from the radio. Rao Shinpo and Kashu Mainichi also reported the news. After Pearl Harbor, they left for Denver for the voluntary evacuation with their two daughters, ages 11 and 9 at the time.
    At the time of the interview, the older daughter was 50 and living in Los Angeles, where she owned a flower boutique. The younger daughter was 48 and living in Watsonville. As there were no Japanese groceries available in Denver, he and his wife started a business to supply Japanese food (fermented bean paste, soy sauce, etc) to the camp.They hired 100 Japanese people to work with them. Most of them either lived in Denver or moved there for the voluntary relocation. He also hired people from the camp who were from the same hometown. On his most profitable days, his business made $4,000 per day. He didn’t experience any prejudice in building his business and has never experienced prejudice at all in the United States. He stayed in Denver from the beginning of the war until the end, altogether 5-6 years. In his experience, the camp was very good. They fed the Japanese whatever they needed, and some loved it so much they later said they wished they could go back. In his opinion, camp life was luxurious. Every three months or so, the wife of President Roosevelt came to visit them. However, Poston Camp No. 1, compared with other camps, was not very good. They offered no mush or fruits for the meals. The food service was not good. It was the Japanese food servers’ fault. They did not distribute food equally and, as a result, the meal situation was very bad. Kokichi’s company only provided food to the camp. He never got involved with clothing. After the war, he took $5,000 from the government as compensation. With the $5,000, he went to the Watsonville. He had lots of childhood friends there, and heard strawberry farming was profitable. He didn’t make any money, so he opened an import/export business. As Japan was so poor, he went to Kagoshima and created a Satsumayaki (Satsuma pottery) company to ship pottery to the United States. It didn’t do well. Then, in Kumamoto, he created a togarashi (hot pepper) company, and it was successful. His business attitude is to respect whoever he is dealing with and not to put too much weight on making money. This attitude comes from his faith. He turned to Christianity when he was sick in Taiwan and his faith helped to heal him. He likes the United States better, but he tries to help Japan as he still considers himself to be Japanese.
    Kokichi has a column in Kashu Mainichi, which he has been writing in for 30 years.
    He had 8 grandchildren and 4 great-grandchildren (11 years old is oldest) at the time of interview. One of his grandsons died in the Vietnam War.
    Kasato Maru (Ship).; Kashu mainichi shinbun .; Nakamura, Harukichi; Nakamura, Heikichi; Nakamura, Iekichi; Satsuma pottery.; Chiran-chō (Japan); Denver (Colo.); Los Angeles (Calif.); Taiwan; Vietnam War, 1961-1975; Watsonville (Calif.)
    - Interview, May 7, 1978, 1978-05-07; 2 audiocassettes
  - 13. Frank Sakata, 1981-01-19 and 1981-01-28; Sakata, Frank
    Interview of Kyuzaburo Sakata, a successful farmer and a businessman by his son, Frank Sakata. The interviewee, Mr. Frank Sakai, went to school in Lompoc, CA. He finished grammar school and high school in Watsonville, then majored in economics at San Jose State College. This interview is about his father, Kyuzaburo Sakata. Kyuzaburo Sakata was born February 4, 1885 in Hidaka-gun, Wakayama-ken. Kyuzaburo passed away on Aug. 23, 1971, at the age of 86. In 1908, a Jewish business friend gave him the name Harry, so he began to use the name “H.K. Sakata” on some occasions. Kyuzaburo was the oldest son among three brothers and two sisters. His family farmed and fished. He asked his parents to let him go to the U.S. and they gave in when he was 15 years old, allowing him to go to Steveston, British Columbia, Canada to join his uncle. He stayed with his uncle for two years, then came to the United States in 1902 to join his fellow villagers in Lompoc, CA. He was a common farm laborer at first. Later, he became a partner with his two of his cousins and farmed with them on a share arrangement. They did well and were able to buy twenty acres of land before the Alien Land Law was enacted in 1913. He married a sister of one of his cousins in 1910. Her name is Tomie Ishida Sakata, and she was born in May 1892. At the time of their marriage, he was 28 and she was 20. He sold the land to an American man at an excellent value. His two cousins went home to Japan with quite a substantial amount of money. Kyuzaburo then relocated to Watsonville in Dec. 1917. He received legal advice from attorney Guy C. Calden suggesting that he could circumvent the land law by forming a corporation. The L & W Company was organized, bought land, and began farming in 1918. Their association lasted until Mr. Calden’s death. Kyuzaburo had business partnership with M. A. Travers from 1925 to 1937. He became a citizen in 1953, one year after it was allowed for the Japanese.
    Calden, Guy C.; Sakata, H.K.; Sakata, Harry; Sakata, Kyuzaburo; Tomie, Ishida Sakata; Travers, M. A.; Hidaka-gun (Japan); Lompoc (Calif.); Poston (Ariz.); Steveston (B.C.)
    - Transcript, 1 folder (Text 3, Folder 11)
  - 14. Masasuke (Mack) and Hiroko Shikuma, 1981-01-29; Shikuma, Hiroko; Shikuma, Masasuke
    Mr. Shikuma was born in 1907 in Monterey County. This interview is mostly about his father, Mr. Unosuke Shikuma, who was a successful businessman. Mr. Unosuke Shikuma was born in Shinjo-mura, Yamaguchi-ken. He was born April 13, 1884 (Meiji 17). He came to the United States when he was about 18 years old. He went to Christian Mission School, where they taught English to Japanese people in Watsonville. He worked as a strawberry farmer. Mr. Unosuke Shikuma was taken by the FBI to the local police station for questioning in March after the war broke out. Since everyone had to leave for Poston, Arizona, they transferred their businesses to their Italian partner, Mr. Tomasello, with whom they farmed before the war. Mr. Unosuke Shikuma passed away on Jan. 4, 1969.
    Shikuma, Unosuke
    - Interview, January 29, 1981: Interviewee's Copy, 1981-01-29; 2 audiocassettes
    - Interview, January 29, 1981, 1981-01-29; 2 audiocassettes
    - Transcript, 1 folder (Text 3, Folder 12)
  - 15. Yuki Torigoe, 1978-04-26 and 1978-05-26; Torigoe, Yuki
    This is an interview with Yuki Torigoe. It contains her biographical information as well as that of her husband, Bunkichi Torigoe. Yuki Torigoe was born on Feb. 19, 1896 (Meiji 29). She was 12 years younger than her husband. Bunkichi Torigoe was born July 16, Meiji 17 (1884) in Kurashiki, Okayama prefecture. Bunkichi, the first-born son, had a younger brother and sister. He came to United States when he was 15 years and 7 months old. He arrived first in Vancouver, then came down to Seattle and went to North Dakota to work for the railroad. After that, he moved to San Francisco, where he worked in a kitchen assisting the cook. When he was about 20 years old, he moved to Watsonville. The following year, Bunkichi started a grocery store called “Hokoku Shokai” in Salinas with five or six Japanese friends, which eventually went bankrupt. During this period, Bunkichi taught himself to repair watches, bicycles and motorcycles. When he was 23, with the bankruptcy of the “Hokoku Shokai” grocery store, he opened his own grocery store. He sold bicycles and motorcycles and fixed watches on the side. He managed the store by himself. His younger brother and younger sister came to U.S. as well. Yuki Torigoe also came from a farming family. They cultivated igusa, which they used to weave “kaen,” or Hanamushiro (goza mattresses). Yuki has one older sister and one younger brother in Imai, Kibi-gun, Japan. Bunkichi was a relative, although not a blood relative as Bunkichi’s grandfather was adopted into the family. Yuki came to the U.S. by herself when she was 18 years old in 1914. She had never met Bunkichi before their marriage. Bunkichi was 30 years old at that time. Bunkichi had been married before to a mail-order bride. Yuki and Bunkichi had four children, two boys and two girls. The oldest daughter was born in 1915 and their second daughter, who lives in Japan now, is named Toyoko and was born in 1917. The oldest daughter teaches Japanese in Castroville. Their oldest son, Setsuo, was born in 1918 and is a dentist in San Jose, and their second son, Kenji was born in May 1926 and is a dentist in Campbell. Due to the bad economy, Yuki went back to Japan in 1918 when she was 23 years old and took three of her children to get them educated. Setsuo and Yuki went back to the United States after two years, but the daughters stayed behind in Kurashiki with Yuki’s parents. After they graduated from Katahira Kenkyuka women’s high school, Yuki called them back to the U.S., since Yuki’s father passed away. Setsuo went to university in St. Louis, and war broke out during his third year. Bunkichi was taken to an interment camp in North Dakota immediately after Pearl Harbor since he had sold guns. Yuki, her two daughters and nieces, and friends all went to voluntary evacuation in Colorado in February, 1942. They went to Daiko Danchi ranch in the country. Their second son was 16 years old and still in high school. After he finished high school, he was drafted to fight in the 442nd Regiment. Their older son, Setsuo, was in dental school in St. Louis for two years, then opened his practice in Colorado. They were still in Colorado after the war ended. Yuki came back to Watsonville in 1948 to find everything in their store stolen. They did not submit a claim of compensation to the U.S. government since Bunkichi said it was too hard to list everything he had lost. They opened a new store in 1948 in Watsonville. Bunkichi managed his store (Torigoe store, on Main Street) until his death in 1970. He received his US citizenship in 1952. Yuki didn’t receive hers, since she still had land and a house in Japan.
    Hattori, Kathy; Koga, Sumio, Rev.; Torigoe, Bunkichi; Torigoe, Setsuo; Torigoe, Toyoko; Kurashiki-shi (Japan); Salinas (Calif.)
    - Interview, April 26, 1978, 1978-04-26; 2 audiocassettes
    - Interview, May 26, 1978, 1978-05-26; 2 audiocassettes
    - Transcripts, 1 folder (Text 3, Folder 13)
  - 16. Eiko Tsuyuki, 1978-04-05; Tsuyuki, Eiko
    The interviewee is Mrs. Eiko Tsuyuki. Her father, Takejiro Okuhara, was born in Kumage-gun, Yamaguchi prefecture, to a family of farmers. Being a second son, he didn’t have any land of his own, so he went to Canada, where he worked for a lumber company. Mrs. Tsuyuki was born in Vancouver, British Columbia, Canada in 1903 but was sent to Japan for her education at the age of 5. Since her uncle and aunt had no children, they took care of her and raised her. Her uncle is her father’s twin brother.
    She had no memory of her mother, Katsu Tsuyuki, who died in Vancouver when she was 9 years old and still living in Japan. She has one brother and one sister who passed away by the time of the interview.
    Mrs. Tsuyuki went to United States when she was 18 years old, in 1921, when she married. Her first husband, Kyosuke Kishimura, was born in Kuga-gun, Yamaguchi prefecture. Mr. Kishimura came to Japan to get married and to take his wife to the United States. The marriage was arranged by a go-between (baishaku kekkon). Her neighbors, the Matsumotos, arranged the marriage.
    The couple went to Watsonville, CA in 1922. He packed apples in the winter and, in the summer, he worked on Mr. Unosuke Shikuma’s farm in Watsonville. Mr. Kishimura was a half-share tenant farmer and grew strawberries and tomatoes. In April 1942, they went to a temporary camp in Salinas. On July 4, 1942, they were sent to Camp #2 in Poston, Arizona.
    Mr. Kishimoto and Mrs. Tsuyuki had two daughters. During their stay in camp, Mr. Kishimoto, who had angina pectoris, died after suffering a heart attack. Right after her husband died, her older daughter, who was 20 years old, moved out of camp by herself and worked on the East Coast. After she found a job and worked there for a year, she came back to camp to take her mother and younger sister (Yukiko, age 12 at the time) to the East Coast with her. Mrs. Tsuyuki then took the family to Detroit, where she worked as a domestic helper for three years. Mrs. Tsuyuki’s older daughter was engaged to a man in Watsonville, which is why they returned there. Mrs. Tsuyuki’s second marriage was after the war in Watsonville. Mr. Tsuyuki had been a bachelor for a long time. His daughter, Mrs. Miura, asked Mrs. Tsuyuki to marry him.
    Hattori, Kathy; Kishimura, Kyosuke; Koga, Sumio, Rev.; Okuhara, Takejiro; Shikuma, Unosuke; Tsuyuki, Katsu; Tsuyuki, Yukiko; Kumage-chō (Japan)
    - Interview, April 5, 1978, 1978-04-05; 1 audiocassette
    - Interview, April 5, 1978: Interviewee's Copy, 1978-04-05; 1 audiocassette
    - Transcripts, 1 folder (Text 3, Folder 14)
  - 17. Ichiro Yamaguchi, 1978-05-05; Yamaguchi, Ichiro
    Interview was conducted in English. The interviewee is Mr. Ichiro Yamaguchi. Mr. Yamaguchi was the first son. He was born in Watsonville on July 21, 1908, and grew up on a strawberry farm. During the war, he went to Oregon to join the Sakatas, who had a ranch there. Mr. Yamaguchi’s father, Masaki Yamaguchi, changed his first name from Otokichi since his uncle (Otokichi Kajioka) had the same name. He came from Fukui-ken in Japan and was partners in the J. S. Kosansha (Kosansha was one of the Japanese farmers' companies). Masaki Yamaguchi came to the United States in 1900. Masaki Yamaguchi’s marriage was listed in the “Shinsekai” newspaper. He owned a car after 1915, which was rather early. Masaki began growing lettuce after World War I. Ichiro and his brother helped their father before and after school, and by working so hard they both got pneumonia. Masaki gained US citizenship in the same year he died, at the age of 100. Ichiro’s mother, Shina, became sick when Ichiro was around four years old and went to San Francisco Hospital (then Stanford hospital). She went back to Japan, and died there when Ichiro was about 8 years old. She took two daughters (Ichiro’s sisters, one a baby and other 2-3 years old) with her. Ichiro’s aunt and uncle took care of them. When Masaki became sick, Ichiro was 17 or 18. Since Ichiro and his brother couldn’t farm on their own, they quit the farm when their lease ran out and went to work for their uncle as regular employees. They called their sisters from Japan to take care of their sick father and worked on the side. After six or seven years of illness, the father got better and lived another fifty years. Ichiro went to Carlton School. He was the first Japanese to go there. After Pearl Harbor, they were moved to Salinas Assembly Center and then were sent to Poston, Arizona in July 1942. In Oct. 1942, they went to work harvesting sugar beets in Nebraska. Ichiro’s wife stayed in the camp. He worked for Mr. Kyusaburo Sakata. Then, after the war, his brother, several of his brother’s relatives, and Mr. Toshio Matsushita, bought the land from Mr. Sakata. They lived in Oregon for 11 years. They came back to Watsonville in 1955. He grew strawberries for a while, but went almost bankrupt. Then, he worked for his neighbors, who were produce growers. After working for them for 2-3 years, he went into gardening in about 1963 as there was more money in gardening.
    Kajioka, Otokichi; Matsushita, Toshio; Sakata, Kyuzaburo; Yamaguchi, Masaki; Yamaguchi, Otokichi; Yamaguchi, Shina; Poston (Ariz.)
    - Interview, May 5, 1982, 1982-05-05; 2 audiocassettes
    - Interview, May 5, 1982: Interviewee's Copy, 1982-05-05; 2 audiocassettes
    - Transcript, 1 folder (Text 3, Folder 15)